<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd in the chappel of His Excellency the Spanish embassador on the second Sunday of Advent, December 4. 1687. On which was solemniz'd the Feast of St. Francis Xaverius, of the Society of Jesus, apostle of the Indies and Kingdom of Japan. By the R.F. Lewis Sabran of the same Society. Permissu superiorum.</title>
            <author>Sabran, Lewis, 1652-1732.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58916</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S221A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219047</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830583</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830583</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35036</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58916)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35036)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1875:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd in the chappel of His Excellency the Spanish embassador on the second Sunday of Advent, December 4. 1687. On which was solemniz'd the Feast of St. Francis Xaverius, of the Society of Jesus, apostle of the Indies and Kingdom of Japan. By the R.F. Lewis Sabran of the same Society. Permissu superiorum.</title>
                  <author>Sabran, Lewis, 1652-1732.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Henry Hills, printer to the King's most excellent Majesty, for His houshold and chappel; and are sold at his printing-house on the Ditch-side in Black-Fryers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Copy stained, with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Francis Xavier, --  Saint, 1506-1552 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:35036:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
A SERMON Preach'd in the Chappel of HIS EXCELLENCY THE <hi>SPANISH EMBASSADOR,</hi> On the Second Sunday of ADVENT, <hi>December</hi> 4. 1687.</p>
            <p>On which was Solemniz'd the Feaſt of St. <hi>Francis Xaverius,</hi> of the Society of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> Apoſtle of the <hi>INDIES</hi> and Kingdom of <hi>JAPAN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the R. F. LEWIS SABRA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the ſame Society.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PERMISSU S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PERIOR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by, <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> Printer to the King's Moſt Excellent Majeſty, for His Houſhold and Chappel; And are ſold at his Printing-houſe on the <hi>Ditch-ſide</hi> in <hi>Black-Fryers.</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:35036:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd in the Chappel of his Excellency The <hi>SPANISH</hi> Embaſſador, On the Second <hi>Sunday</hi> of <hi>Advent, December</hi> 4. 1687.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Caeci vident, claudi ambulant, leproſi mudantur, ſurdi audiunt, mortui reſurgunt, pauperes Evangelizan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; beatus qui non fuerit, ſcandalizatus in me.</p>
                  <bibl>Matt. 11. 5, 6.</bibl>
                  <p>The blind ſee, the lame walk, the lepers are cleanſed, the deaf hear, the dead riſe to life, the poor have the Goſpel preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them, and happy is he who is not ſcandalized in me.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a weighty Doubt which, in this <hi>Sundays</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, St. <hi>John</hi> moves by his Diſciples, his Chains not allowing him the liberty to offer it himſelf to our Bleſſed Lord to be reſolved; <note n="a" place="margin">Tu es qui venturus es. <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>Are you he who is to come?</hi> Are you that Saviour whom for ſo many Ages the ſighing Prophets have ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, gracious Heaven hath promiſed, the longing Earth expected? An Important <hi>Quaere!</hi> For what can be of a nearer concern, than not to miſtake our God? <note n="b" place="margin">Haec eſt vita aeterna ut cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcant te ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Deum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; quem miſiſti Jeſum Chriſtum. <hi>Joan.</hi> 17.</note> 'Tis that Life everlaſting which we hope for, <hi>to know</hi> by the light of <hi>Glory, our ſole true God, and him he hath ſent, Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> And 'tis the only way leading to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35036:3"/>
that Life, to know Both here by the light of <hi>Faith.</hi> But doth the <hi>Voice</hi> then queſtion the <hi>Word</hi> that formed and ſent it? Is that Head-Myſtery concealed from St. John, <hi>than whom a greater Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet is not born of a Woman?</hi> No certainly: The Eternal Father lately bore in his preſence witneſs to Chriſt at the Bank of the River <hi>Jordan;</hi> Even when yet inclos'd in his Mothers Womb he owned his Lord, and Propheſied of him before he could ſpeak; Lately he proclaimed him to be <hi>the Lamb of God,</hi> which takes away the Sins of the World; Tis at the very propoſal of this Doubt, that he receives that high Character of <note n="c" place="margin">Major inter natos mulie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum propheta Joanne Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſta nemo eſt. <hi>Luc. 7. Joan.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>More than a Prophet,</hi> becoming by this his Embaſſy alſo an Apoſtle: for, <note n="d" place="margin">Ut ſibi quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens, illis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſceret. <hi>Hier ad Aglas.</hi>
               </note> as St. <hi>Jerom</hi> obſerves, St. <hi>John</hi> propoſes the Doubt of his miſtaken Diſciples, that they may be inſtructed by <hi>Jeſus</hi> his Anſwer. 'Tis <hi>their Ignorance,</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Non ſuae ſed diſcipulorum ignorantiae Joannes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulit. <hi>Hil. ſup. Matt.</hi>
               </note> ſays S. Hilary, <hi>that he deſigns to remove, not his own Knowledge that he would improve.</hi> Chriſtians of <hi>England,</hi> (if I may call by one Name People of ſo different a Belief, of ſuch oppoſit Perſuaſions) the Church of God asks in her Goſpel the ſame Queſtion this Day. <hi>Tu es? Are you the Lord?</hi> And well ſhe may, when ſhe finds her Subjects ſo divided about him. <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>Here is Chriſt,</hi> ſays one, with my Band only. No, <hi>There is Chriſt</hi> in that other different Party, ſays a Second. He is <hi>within,</hi> ſays a Third; this <hi>Private Spirit</hi> of mine ſingles him from amongſt the falſe ones. He was <hi>in the Wilderneſs,</hi> another pretends; there he had been hidden for many Ages, till we <hi>lately</hi> diſcover'd him. Thus each Sect, each Party, each Diviſion challenges him. He is not in all theſe ſo different, ſo oppoſite Beliefs: for <hi>he is not</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Non enim eſt diſſentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Deus ſed pacis. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>the God of Diſſention, but of Peace</hi> and Unity. To correct theſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Errors, to redreſs ſo dangerous Miſtakes, the true Church, in imitation of St. <hi>John,</hi> asks him this Day the ſame Queſtion, <hi>Tu es?</hi> Are you the Lord? you that are Adored by my Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Worſhipped on my Altars?</p>
            <p>I know each Sect will anſwer, <hi>Here he is,</hi> this is his true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which I pay. But we are never the nearer, ſome unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and potent Proof muſt be offered. Hence our Bleſſed Lord anſwered not the Diſciples of St. <hi>John</hi> by a bare Aſſertion, <hi>I am he.</hi> All Deceivers and Antichriſtian Cheats could give in that Anſwer for themſelves; each falſe Prophet was ever the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt to cry out, <hi>The Word of the Lord,</hi> the pure Word of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35036:3"/>
Lord. <hi>Jeſus</hi> brought <hi>Facts</hi> in lieu of <hi>Words;</hi> and elſewhere aſſures us, that if he had <note n="g" place="margin">Si ego teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monium per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibeo de me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſo, teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium meum non eſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. <hi>Joan.</hi> 5. 31.</note> with bare words born witneſs to himſelf, and challenged thereupon to be believed, it ought to have been held <hi>as a falſe one,</hi> and not to have been regarded. This was his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>The blind ſee, the lame walk, the lepers are cleanſed, the deaf hear, the dead riſe to life.</hi> Behold the <hi>Firſt</hi> Proof and Mark, <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles,</hi> unqueſtionable by reaſon of their greatneſs, number, evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. <hi>The poor are preached unto;</hi> behold the <hi>Second,</hi> to wit, thoſe unuſual Means (humanly of no force) uſed to convert and ſubdue the World, by poor, ſilly, ignorant Men; and again, their refuſal of all human Helps towards ſo vaſt an Enterpriſe. <hi>And happy is he who is not ſcandalized in me;</hi> behold the <hi>Third,</hi> to wit, thoſe eminent ſupernatural Gifts and Bleſſings beſtowed on thoſe who embraced his Poverty and Abjection, ſo unknown un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or deſpiſed by the World, which were undeniable Proofs of his Apoſtles Holineſs. We agree all about the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by thoſe undoubted Marks now obſerved; but many are the more miſerable and guilty, whilſt they debate about his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin and Law, and ſo neither receive the one, nor obey the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. How ſhall a well-meaning Man clear theſe Doubts, and find out his true, Doctrin, Church, Worſhip, whom he owns to be his God and Redeemer? Could any of this Churches Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes give the ſame Evidence and Proofs which Chriſt gave for himſelf, our Differences would be at an end, our Doubts cleared, our Faith ſetled. Chriſtian Auditors, God moſt mercifully offers us many, one I will produce this Day, <hi>the great Apoſtle of the</hi> Indies, <hi>and the Kingdoms of</hi> Japan, <hi>Xaverius.</hi> All things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur to move me to ſpeak of him. <hi>Firſt</hi> my Text; for I intend to prove, that his Life and Actions give the ſame Anſwer, the ſame Proofs for the truth of the Catholic Church, which Chriſt gave to evince himſelf to be the true <hi>Meſſias:</hi> So that if we proceed on thoſe Motives which Chriſt himſelf judged the cleareſt and ſafeſt, we muſt all be <hi>Catholics, or no Chriſtians. Next,</hi> the general Devotion of the <hi>pious</hi> World towards this great Apoſtle of our Days, during this Octave of his Feaſt, exacts it of me. <hi>Again,</hi> the Habit I have the Honor to wear, the Society I am an unworthy Member of, challenges it; a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety he won ſuch a Credit unto, and reciprocally ſo valued,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35036:4"/>
that his laſt Letters from <hi>Cochino</hi> into <hi>Europe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> own, that he mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly eſcaped an infinity of Dangers, by recommending him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Merits and Prayers of the living and deceaſed Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it, that he could make no end when he ſpoke of the value of, and love for it which he had; that he ſhould ſooner forget his <note n="h" place="margin">Cum obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus fuero tui, ſocietas Jeſu, oblivioni de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur dextera mea. <hi>Epiſt. l. 2. Ep. 2. Ex Card. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton. Zapata.</hi>
               </note> own Right-hand, than that tenderneſs. In fine, this very Chappel of the Catholic King forbids me to paſs by a Saint of the Royal Blood of <hi>Navar,</hi> whoſe prodigious Succeſs in Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Labors, hath gained to <hi>Spain</hi> the glorious Character which St. <hi>Proſper</hi> gave to <hi>Catholic Rome,</hi> to wit, That <note n="i" place="margin">Quidquid non poſſidet armis Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one tenet. <hi>Carm. de Ing.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>what Parts of the World her Sword hath not ſubdued to her Empire, her Piety and Religion hath Conquered for Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Maria ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta Mater Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini noſtri Jeſu Chriſti, obtine pro no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis ab amabili filio tuo ut credamus hanc verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſine ullo dubio. <hi>Epiſt. l. 1. Ep.</hi> 5.</note> Sacred Virgin, the great <hi>Xaverius</hi> never begun a Sermon or Catechiſm, without begging by your Interceſſion the Knowledge and Practice of the Vertue he treated of: In Imitation of him, I beg of your Divine Son, by the <hi>Mediation</hi> of your <hi>Interceſſion,</hi> that I may even to the moſt wilfully blind of Sectaries, ſhew in the Life and <hi>miraculous</hi> Actions of <hi>Xaverius,</hi> the moſt evident Proofs of true Religion and Piety, to be found only in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Church; and to the Members thereof, the Security of their <hi>Faith,</hi> the Sanctity of their <hi>Law,</hi> the Piety of their <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>AVE MARIA.</q>
            <p>OUR Bleſſed Lord being to give convincing Proofs of his Divinity to St. <hi>John</hi>'s Diſciples, ſuch as by their Evidence ſhould lay them and the whole Nation of the <hi>Jews</hi> under a clear Obligation of owning him; drew them not from the written Law, or any part of Holy Scripture, nor from any Character of Divinity, or any ſuch ſelf-perſuading Truth that appeared in his holy Word, tho' uttered from his own Bleſſed Mouth, or from the Holineſs of his Principles, the Sanctity and Congruity of his whole Doctrin; ſuch Marks could be comprehended by few, or were the very Points in Debate. He took them from plain Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Fact,</hi> expoſed to the dulleſt, proportioned to the meaneſt Capacities; for ſuch ought to be the Proofs of a Religion, which excluded none from its Profeſſion, but opened Heaven equally
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35036:4"/>
to all. This was the firſt, the grand and certain Motive of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibility, diſpoſing all to reduce their Underſtandings unto a due, humble ſubjection to Faith, <hi>The blind ſee, the lame walk, the leprous are cleanſed, the deaf hear, the dead are raiſed to life.</hi> By which he left to each Man this Argument to frame; Where ſuch evident Prodigies are wrought, 'tis clear, that Gods Hand ſubſcribes to the Doctrin in Evidence whereof they are brought; But Gods infinite Veracity cannot atteſt, and his equal Bounty cannot ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit us to be moſt credibly perſuaded, that he does atteſt an Untruth; Therefore all that Chriſt teaches is true, he is then the Son of God, ſince he declares himſelf to be ſo. In the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his Preaching he had expoſed to the <hi>Jews</hi> the ſame Motive, by which he pretended they were to be convinced of their Obligation of receiving him, to wit, becauſe <note n="a" place="margin">Hunc enim ſignavit Deus. <hi>Joan.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sealed</hi> his Commiſſion by which he authoriſed him to Preach. Some Ages before the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> warned that incredulous Nation, that the clear Marks by which they ſhould undoubtedly know this great Prophet, ſhould be theſe ſelf-ſame <note n="b" place="margin">Tunc aperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entur oculi caecorum &amp; aures ſurdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum tunc pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebunt; &amp; ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet tanquam Cervus clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.</note> 
               <hi>miraculous Cures of their Sick, their blind, their lame, their leprous.</hi> Which Wonders were ſo convincing, that our Bleſſed Lord owned to the <hi>Jews,</hi> that altho' they refuſed to yield to thoſe Motives which he offered them in his Sermons, yet they could not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out obſtinacy refuſe <note n="c" place="margin">Opera quae Ego facio te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonium perhibent de me, illis cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite ſi verbis non vultis. <hi>Joan</hi> 10.</note> a <hi>Belief to his Works,</hi> which could part from no other Hand but that of God. Such was their Blindneſs, yet ſuch alſo was the Light his Miracles did yield towards the diſcovery of the Truths which he taught them, that he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged they might have found an Excuſe for their Inſidelity, and <hi>without ſin</hi> have refuſed to ſubmit to him, had he not <note n="d" place="margin">Si opera non feciſſem in illis quae ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo alius fecit, peccatum non haberent. <hi>Joan. 15. 1 Cor. 4. 2 Cor.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>wrought greater Miracles than any before amongſt them,</hi> to which conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently no other like Miracles could be pretended to be oppoſed; and therefore nothing that might weaken their Divine Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, to which they could not without a heinous ſin refuſe Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and an entire Submiſſion. This was the Method uſed by Chriſt, as the moſt natural and clear, the moſt capable to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer Mens proud, yet dull Minds, and to faſten their unſteddy and wavering Hearts, to Faith and Religion.</p>
            <p>His Apoſtles uſed the ſame. To inſtance in one; St. <hi>Paul</hi> challenges a ſubmiſſive Belief to what he had Preached, from
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35036:5"/>
the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> becauſe he had proved himſelf an <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> not only by his <hi>Patience,</hi> (the true Teſt of Real and Solid Virtue) but alſo by <hi>Signs, Prodigies, and Power:</hi> And there being ſome falſe Apoſtles who oppos'd him, ſeduc'd from him his <hi>Neophytes,</hi> and valu'd themſelves much on their Preaching and Diſcourſes; he minds them that the Word of God is not chiefly atteſted by <hi>Words,</hi> but by <hi>Power.</hi> And indeed, as St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, <note n="a" place="margin">Quando no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum a liquid, fit &amp; praecipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, ſigna De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us facere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuevit, praeſtat qurdam pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora ſuae po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae, iisqui legem ejus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiunt. <hi>Chryſ. ho. 14. in Mat.</hi>
               </note> when God declares any <hi>new thing,</hi> or orders any of <hi>great importance,</hi> (and ſuch is, if any, a General Reformation in Faith) <hi>he uſes to work Wonders, yielding ſome pledges of his Power to thoſe who receive his Law.</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Adjuncta ſunt paaedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toribus mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula ut Fidem verbis daret virtus oſtenſa: &amp; Nova face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent qui nova praedicarent. <hi>Greg. hom. 4. in Evang.</hi> Ut magnitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem promiſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum probet magnitudo ſignorum. <hi>Hier. Matt.</hi> 10. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmos curate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He joyned,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Gregory, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles</hi> to <hi>Preaching,</hi> that ſuch an appearance of <hi>Power</hi> ſhould give credit to <hi>Words,</hi> and their Works ſhould be <hi>unuſual,</hi> whoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin was <hi>new. That their great Promiſes,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Hierom, ſhould find a fit warrant in equally great Wonders.</hi> Hence we no ſooner read that Chriſt had choſen Twelve Apoſtles, and had <hi>ſent</hi> them, but that we find him ſigning their Miſſion with theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing words: <hi>Healthe Sick, raiſe the Dead, cleanſe the Leprous, caſt out Devils.</hi> And that we might not believe theſe ſingular Graces to attend only the firſt Apoſtles, he aſſures us, without any limitation of Time or Place, That <hi>thoſe who believe in him,</hi> (John 14.) <hi>ſhall do the ſame Works which He did, and greater than thoſe;</hi> that ſuch Signs and Wonders <hi>ſhall follow thoſe who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</hi> From this clear Method, and plain Doctrin of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and from this following unqueſtionable Truth, grounded on God's Goodneſs and Juſtice, to wit, That <hi>as men are bound to receive the Doctrin which God ſends his Servants to preach to them, ſo he cannot induce them into an Error, by permitting it to be propoſed in his Name, and upheld by Prodigies, which may prudently be believed to be wrought by his hand;</hi> it follows,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That Miracles are clear proofs by which may be reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved all doubts about queſtioned Revelations, and conſequently that there be undoubted Marks to know them by, otherwiſe they would be uſeleſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That God in his Mercy cannot permit that a man, ſlily covering his falſe Doctrin, pretending to be ſent by him, and to teach only what is conformable to what he hath hitherto revealed in holy Scripture, ſhould work Miracles to uphold
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35036:5"/>
Falſhood; and that no one of thoſe who oppoſe him, ſhould work greater in defence of Truth. Theſe Principles being thus cleared and ſettled, I form this Argument for Chriſtianity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Pagan,</hi> to which I crave your attention, that you may obſerve if it faulters in any part, or whether it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes not rather in favour of Us <hi>Chriſtians</hi> an impoſſibility of being miſtaken in adoring Chriſt, and an evident Obligation to it.</p>
            <p>If there were ſuch Perſons as <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and if they wrought ſuch clear Miracles in Proof of the Doctrin which they taught, as are related in the Teſtament; it is certain that all men, ſufficiently informed of thoſe Miracles, are bound to receive their Doctrin as a Truth revealed by God. But there were ſuch Men, and ſuch Miracles wrought by them, and we are all ſufficiently informed of them; therefore we are all bound to believe and profeſs the Doctrin taught by <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> that is, to be <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is this Argument plain and convincing, or no? May not the <hi>Major</hi> Propoſition, if deny'd, be eaſily proved beyond the poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of a Reply, out of the two Principles before laid open? As for the <hi>Minor,</hi> no one can refuſe his aſſent to it, who conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders how thoſe <hi>Miracles</hi> were wrought, in the ſight of great Multitudes, of which moſt were declared Enemies to Chriſt and his Diſclples; how the Records we find them in, were handed to us from Eye-witneſſes, without any probable Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ever being oppoſed to their Truth; how they were owned by the very Enemies of Chriſt for true Records; how the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Effects of thoſe Prodigies remain in the wonderful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the World to Chriſtianity; how they have equally been ſealed with the Blood of Martyrs, the Virtues and Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Gifts of Confeſſors; how theſe Perſons, and their miraculous Works, were propheſied before, and ſuch Prophecies, preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the hands of their Enemies, did point out all the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances that attended their Perſons and Miracles; how (to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude) no other Religion or Belief was ever thus evidently at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted by the Omnipotency of God, ever thus viſibly ſubſcribed unto with his Hand, and marked with his Seal.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:35036:6"/>
Say, Chriſtians, are theſe Proofs clear and convincing? Yea, or No? Do you believe your ſelves ſtrictly bound under pain of Eternal Damnation to believe God, ſpeaking to you as plainly, as theſe Miraculous Proofs convince you, that 'tis He who ſpoke by Chriſt and his Apoſtles? Yes, or No? Yes? we may then well conclude our ſelves all bound to be Chriſtians, and we may convince <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſuch as are not wilfully obſtinate, of their obligation to become Proſely<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es to our Religion.</p>
            <p>But now we are at variance amongſt our ſelves. Theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments I have offered convince indeed each of us, that what Chriſt and his Apoſtles did teach was the Truth; that all who can come to the Knowledge of that Faith which they preach'd, that Religion which they ſetl'd, that Church which they form'd, are bound under pain of Eternal Damnation to embrace that Faith, to profeſs that Religion, and to be Members of that Church: but we differ as to the other main Point, to wit, <hi>what</hi> Faith they did preach, <hi>what</hi> Religion they ſettled, <hi>what</hi> Church they formed. To reduce then all diſſenting Chriſtians to one Faith, one Religion, one Church, what can be a more infallible and unqueſtionable Motive, than to uſe the ſame Argument which moves us all to be Chriſtians? Which I thus offer, altering only ſuch words in it which fit it to our Caſe, without taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way any thing from its force.</p>
            <p>If there was ſuch a man as <hi>Xaverius,</hi> and if he wrought ſuch clear Miracles in proof of the Doctrin which he taught, as are related in all the Hiſtories of the <hi>Indies,</hi> and of <hi>Japan,</hi> and in his Life written in all Countries and Languages; it is certain that all men, ſufficiently inform'd of thoſe Miracles, are bound to receive his Doctrin, as a Truth revealed by God. But there was ſuch a Man, and ſuch Miracles wrought by him, and we are all (or may be when we pleaſe) ſufficiently informed of them; therefore we are all bound to believe and profeſs the Doctrin taught by him, that is to be <hi>Roman Catholics.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is this Argument clear and convincing? If ſo, why are we not Catholics? If not, how are we Chriſtians, induced to it by the former, which is the very ſame with this? All that needs then to be attempted, is only to evince the parity; which I ſhall do, <hi>firſt,</hi> by expoſing in ſhort to your view thoſe admirable Miracles
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35036:6"/>
of <hi>Xaverius,</hi> which will appear to be the ſame with thoſe that were wrought by the <hi>Prophets,</hi> by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by his <hi>Apoſtles; next,</hi> by ſhewing that no Objection can be made againſt them, which may not be of equal force in a <hi>Pagan</hi>'s or a <hi>Jew</hi>'s mouth, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Miracles and Prodigies wrought by the Prophets, by Chriſt, by his Apoſtles. If I make good theſe two Points, this Concluſion will unavoidable follow: Whoever is a Chriſtian on the true grounds of Chriſtianity, muſt alſo be a Catholic; or if no Catholic, no Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>The Prodigies which God wrought by St. <hi>Xaverius</hi> were ſuch, that I dare ſay of them in general, they are the beſt Inſtance the Church of God hath had, from the firſt Apoſtles time, of the truth of two Promiſes of Chriſt; the firſt, <note n="*" place="margin">Ecce, ego vobiſcum ſum uſque ad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummationem ſaeculi.</note> 
               <hi>Mat. 28. Behold, I ſhall be with you to the conſummation of Ages;</hi> the ſecond, † <hi>John 14. The Works which I do, they ſhall do; and greater than theſe they ſhall do.</hi> What greater Miracles can be an evident proof of a Prophet's or an Apoſtle's Miſſion, than to command and alter <note n="†" place="margin"> 
                  <hi rend="sup">b</hi> Opera quae ego facio ipſe faciet &amp; majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra horum ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciet.</note> the Elements, to cure all Diſeaſes, to be obey'd by the muteſt Fiſhes and wildeſt Beaſts, to dive into Human Hearts and Thoughts, to break even the Bonds of Death, and reſtore to Life? Add to theſe, the Gift of Tongues, and that of Propheſie. All theſe Graces St. <hi>Xaverius</hi> poſſeſt in a large meaſure, and the Miracles he wrought are in their credibility as unqueſtionable, as thoſe we ground Chriſtianity upon.</p>
            <p>To inſtance in ſome few, but wrought in ſuch circumſtances as remove all doubt: A great Miracle it was, when after three years drouth the Heavens, at the moment foretold by <hi>Elias,</hi> gathered into Clouds, theſe yielded to his firſt requeſt abundant <note place="margin">3 Reg. 18.</note> Rain: But was it a leſſer Wonder, or leſs Illuſtrious, when St. <hi>Xaverius</hi> in the Iſland of <hi>Vlata,</hi> the King whereof with his <note place="margin">Bartoli. Afia.</note> whole People were ready to yield up their Liberty and Life to their Enemies Chains or Swords, who held them beſieged, and by turning the Courſe of thoſe Waters which relieved their Town, had already almoſt killed them with drouth; when <hi>Xa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verius,</hi> I ſay, promiſed thoſe Mahometans and Idolaters a ſupply of Water from Heaven, and drew it by his firſt Prayers in ſuch abundance, as forced their Enemies to raiſe the Siege; by which Miracle he converted, with which Waters he baptized them?
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35036:7"/>
Let us reverence the Prophet <hi>Elizeus,</hi> who turned bitter Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <note place="margin">4 <hi>Reg.</hi> 4.</note> into ſweet, to refreſh the Children of the Prophets: but let it not appear leſs prodigious in <hi>Xaverius</hi> to relieve ſeveral times in a greater diſtreſs Seamen and Paſſengers, changing by his Bleſſing ſalt Water into freſh, whil'ſt he broke by his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Turſell. Vit.</hi> Xav.</note> the moſt ſwelling Billows, ſtill'd the moſt ſtormy Winds. The Air, Fire, Earth, obey'd his voice as readily as the Water; when in the Iſland of <hi>Mero,</hi> the one gathered into Clouds, theſe were torn with Thunder and Lightning, followed by moſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying Earthquakes, to ſtrike fear into the more unmovable and deaf hearts of the moſt ſavage and barbarous Inhabitants. To cure the Sick was the Power by which our bleſſed Lord firſt and chiefly enabled his Apoſtles to prove they were ſent by God: whoever had it in a fuller proportion than <hi>Xaverius!</hi> Behold him in the City of <hi>Paſim,</hi> ſurrounded by Three Thouſand Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters all ſtrucken with the Plague; who by his firſt Bleſſing (after a fervent Prayer) were all ſuddenly cur'd; by his ſecond (after a ſufficient Inſtruction) baptiz'd. Moſt remarkable was <note place="margin">4 <hi>Reg.</hi> 5.</note> the Cure of the Leprous <hi>Syrian</hi> General <hi>Naaman,</hi> who obeying the Orders which the Prophet ſent him by his Servant <hi>Giezi,</hi> waſhing himſelf ſeven times in the Waters of <hi>Jordan,</hi> was cleanſed, and perfectly cured. The hand of God appeared not leſs evidently at <hi>Xaverius</hi>'s requeſt, when ſent for in <hi>Japan</hi> by an Ulcerous <hi>Lazarus</hi> of Noble Birth, unwilling to break off his Catechiſm, he commiſſioned his Companion to go, and cure him, by forming on him the holy ſign of the Croſs. But with what <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bartoli V.</hi> Xav.</note> luſtre did this unlimited Power appear at <hi>Malaca,</hi> when after he had walked many nights thro' the Streets of that equally Rich and Sinful City, warning all, with the ringing of a Bell, and with a loud Voice, to pray for thoſe who moſt unhappily perſerved in Mortal Sin; finding at laſt he had but few to joyn in Prayers with him, that he might ſtir in thoſe inſenſible Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, dull to all the threats of the Juſtice of God, ſome ſenſe of his Mercy, he cauſed all the Sick to be brought forth, and at once healed them all; at the ſight whereof a Rabbi, and Prince of the Jewiſh Synagogue, numerous in that City, was converted. The Fiſhes of the Sea pay'd that Obedience they ow'd to our Bleſſed Lord, when after the uſeleſs endeavors of a toilſom <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joan.</hi> 21. 3.</note>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:35036:7"/>
Night, they ſill'd the Nets of the three obedient Fiſhermen: the ſame bleſſed Lord honor'd his Servant <hi>Xaverius</hi> with a more illuſtrious Miracle, when in the <hi>Japan-</hi>Sea of <hi>Cangaxima,</hi> at his Prayer, by his Lord's Power, not only the Nets and Boats of ſome Idolatrous Fiſhermen were filled, but that very Sea, by a Miracle continued to this day, was ſtored with abundance of Fiſh, having till then been very barren. Did Jeſus our God ſhew more patently his Divine Power, than in caſting on the ground with two words, <hi>Ego ſum,</hi> I am He, that wicked Band which came to lay Hands on his Sacred Humanity in the Garden of <hi>Getzemani?</hi> Yet, to verifie his own Promiſe, he wrought a greater wonder by <hi>Xaverius,</hi> when the Saint, to protect the newly-converted Chriſtians of <hi>Travancor,</hi> met undauntedly a fierce Army of the moſt Warlike and Cruel Nation of the <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joan.</hi> 18. 6.</note> the <hi>Badages,</hi> and with theſe words, <hi>I forbid you in the Name of the Living God to advance one ſtep further; Moreover, I</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rſel. V.</hi> Xav.</note> 
               <hi>order you to go back;</hi> firſt fix'd them all by fear, then put them to flight, being on that occaſion firſt ſtiled, <hi>the Great Father,</hi> and all the Subjects of the great King of <hi>Travancor</hi> being by Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation commanded to pay to this Saint the ſame Obedience which they owed to their Sovereign. That Power ſeems to be the moſt boundleſs, which is heard even by thoſe who lie ſo low, <note place="margin">Proc. Canoniz.</note> ſo faſt aſleep in their Graves, to which even Death it ſelf is not deaf. Never did God more fully communicate this Power, than to <hi>Xaverius;</hi> five and twenty ſtood on Record, to whom he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored Life: To an <hi>Arabian Mahometan</hi> he reſtored his Son a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live the fourth day after he had been drowned, falling from off a Ship on full Sails. In the City of <hi>Mutan</hi> he copy'd the Miracle <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luca</hi> 7. 11.</note> wrought by Chriſt at <hi>Naim,</hi> in the ſight of the whole Town, which mournfully followed the Corps of their chiefeſt Burgeſs's Son; in Memory whereof a lofty Croſs was erected on the place. At <hi>Travancor</hi> he moved that other <hi>Nineve,</hi> equally ſinful, but more deaf to her Prophet's Summons, to ask what Miracle they pleaſed for proof of his Miſſion; then, at their inſtance, cauſed a Body bury'd the day before to be digg'd up, view'd by them, owned even by its inſupportable ſtench to be half corrupted, and rendred it its Soul. He opened another Grave at <hi>Malaca</hi> the fourth day after it had receiv'd the dead Son of a pious Matron,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35036:8"/>
and reſtored him alive to his comfortleſs Mother. What ſhall I ſay of that miraculous Gift of Tongues? That it was, which worked the Converſion of the greater part of thoſe three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand which St. <hi>Peter</hi> added to the Flock of Chriſt at his firſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Actor.</hi> 2. 6.</note> This Grace appeared moſt frequently given to <hi>Xaverius:</hi> In a Sea-Voyage to <hi>Amboyna</hi> he was at once underſtood by the <hi>Portugezes,</hi> and <hi>Indians</hi> of moſt different Nations and Languages, which moved all theſe to ask Baptiſm: But much more unuſual, and no where elſe that I remember recorded in Sacred Hiſtory, <note place="margin">Bartoli in Aſia.</note> was that Gift of his, ſo admir'd by the <hi>Japoneſes,</hi> eſpecially at <hi>Amanguchi,</hi> to wit, by one Anſwer to ſatisfie ſix or ſeven ſeveral Queſtions, moved to him at once by thoſe <hi>Bonzies</hi> in the heat of Diſputation. In that Kingdom it was, that twice a day he catechiſed the <hi>Chineſe</hi> Merchants in their own Language, he had never been taught one word of, and ſo became <hi>their</hi> miraculous Apoſtle. <hi>In fine,</hi> the Gift of Prophecy, which was in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Prophets but by meaſure, ſeem'd wholly to reſide in Him: In his familiar Diſcourſes, unobſervable to himſelf, he fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently foretold future Events, which no probable circumſtance could ſuggeſt a gueſs of; to <hi>Voglio,</hi> a charitable Merchant, he foretold the day of his Death, aſſigning him a clear Signal or Warning that he ſhould have of it; to moſt looſe Livers he foretold not only their future Converſion, but the Religious Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der they ſhould enter into, and the Crown of Martyrdom they ſhould at laſt receive. No Prediction could ever bear a more laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miracle, than that by which he aſſured the Pilot who brought him out of <hi>Japan,</hi> that his Ship ſhould never ſuffer Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wreck, but at laſt, without any Damage or Loſs, ſhould fall to pieces in the very place it had been built: Many Heathens ſeveral years after were converted, ſeeing this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy ſo miraculouſly fulfill'd, this Ship ever coming ſafe to the Haven through Tempeſts which Shipwreck'd all others that ſet to Sail with it, the Pilot never fearing Rocks, Shelves, Quickſands, Hurricanes, or thoſe ever fatal Typhons of the <hi>Tapanian</hi> Seas, which he owned he ſhould not have dreaded the more, had his Ship been made of Glaſs, knowing it ſafe enough under the Protection of ſo unerring a Prophet. I conclude with a Prodigy that might ſeem (ſo unuſual it is) almoſt to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35036:8"/>
Belief, had not Fifteen Eye-witneſſes on the one hand, and Six ſcore on the other, atteſted it; to wit, that for Three days he did at the ſame time comfort in their Ship thoſe <hi>Portuguezes</hi> who had ſo faithfully ſhared his Dangers in the Kingdoms of <hi>Japan,</hi> aſſuring them that certainly they ſhould recover their Friends, whom a diſmal Tempeſt had born away in the Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boat; and bare thoſe Fifteen others company in their Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boat, driven above Threeſcore Miles from the Ship, guiding and preſerving it in the midſt of the raging Billows and the higheſt Storms, till it bore up to the Ship again.</p>
            <p>Here I ſtop, to know whether any one can make any Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction againſt theſe few, but clear Inſtances of a Power Divine ever attending <hi>Xaverius,</hi> and Confirming his Doctrin, which would not equally ſtrike at the Miracles wrought by our Bleſſed Lord and his holy Apoſtles. I ſhall neither omit nor diſguiſe any one. Let us weigh them, if you pleaſe.</p>
            <p>Miracles (ſays one) are wrought in the dark, are believed on the Credit of few particular Perſons, which pretend to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſome unuſual Favors, and creep thence into a Legend, by the help of ſome ſuperſtitious Perſon, whoſe Weakneſs or Intereſt inclines to be willingly deceived, or ſlily to impoſe on others. Thus he. But how little can ſuch a Cenſure reach Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, expoſed to the view of whole Towns or Nations, wrought in favor of Mahometans, Idolaters, Jews, to oppoſe their Law, and condemn their Practiſes, owned by the Public and Sworn Depoſitions of ſeveral hundreds? If theſe Surmiſes can blaſt ſuch Miracles, wrought to perſuade a Religion, of which the Witneſſes to them diſowned each Article; how eaſily on the like ground ſhall a Pagan or Jew deny, and even ridicule thoſe which we read in the Holy Goſpel.</p>
            <p>But what Security, ſays another, have we, what Evidence for the matter of Fact, of theſe Miracles? The ſame as can be produced for the Miracles of Chriſt, or for the Bible in which they are couched. If Eye-witneſſes, ſworn to the truth, of unblemiſhed and unqueſtionable Credit, be a good Proof; ſuch, and many in number, by the Command of <hi>John</hi> the Third, King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> were produced by the Biſhop of <hi>Goa,</hi> Grand Vicar of <hi>Malaca,</hi> and all the other Prelates ſpread
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35036:9"/>
over the <hi>Indies.</hi> If Hiſtoriographers never are refuſed a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief when all agree in the ſame Narrative, even Enemies, even ſuch whoſe Intereſt would lead them to aſſert the contrary; If ſtanding Monuments, if the freſh Memory of an incident of high concern, uncontrouled, deliver'd by the general conſent of many Nations, be an undoubted and certain Proof; all theſe jointly atteſt theſe Miracles. This (to inſtance Witneſſes which lie not open to the leaſt ſuſpicion, being Enemies of the Ch. of <hi>Rome)</hi> our Engliſh Miniſter <hi>R. Hackluit</hi> ſtiles him, <hi>The Evangelical Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and Divine Maſter of the Indians, of whoſe excellent Virtues and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Praec. Argl. Navig. Vol. 2. P. 2. Collect. Var. Rel. Ling.</note> 
               <hi>miraculous Works the Indian Hiſtories are full.</hi> The French Calviniſt <hi>Tavernier</hi> owns him <hi>another St.</hi> Paul, <hi>the true Apoſtle of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians. Baldaeus</hi> in his Indian Hiſtory acknowledges him <hi>a true Copy of St.</hi> Paul, <hi>whoſe Gift cannot be expreſs'd or conceived, whom in wonderful Works no one is capable to imitate.</hi> The very <hi>Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> moved by the certain Fame of his unqueſtionable Miracles, built him a <hi>Moſque</hi> in the Coaſt of <hi>Comorino;</hi> the Heathen King of <hi>Travancor</hi> built him a Temple, as the Heathens of <hi>Lyſtris</hi> in <hi>Lycaonia</hi> would have ſacrificed to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> whom by his Miracles they would needs judge to have been one of their Gods in Human, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Actor.</hi> 14.</note> ſhape; and from his time the <hi>Indian</hi> Infidels have ever uſed to ſwear by him in moſt weighty matters. If any one, in favour of the Apoſtles Miracles, urges the Converſion of Nations procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by them; how clear a proof is drawn from thence for St. <hi>Xaverius</hi> his Miracles? So many Nations have by their evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence been drawn from a Lewd, Libertine, and Barbarous Life, to the Meek and Chaſt Humility of Chriſtian Converſation; ſo that I may confirm his Miracles with that Obſervation of St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> concerning thoſe which the Apoſtles are ſaid to have wrought, That if any one would obſtinately deny thoſe of St. <hi>Xaverius,</hi> it were a far greater Miracle that without the working of any he ſhould have converted an infinity of <hi>Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, Jews, Gentiles,</hi> in places ſo remote from any Chriſtian Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, where there was none to countenance or protect thoſe he brought over from their Eſtabliſhed Religion to the Chriſtian Relief and Practices; ſo as to baptize with his own hands above twelve hundred thouſand Infidels.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:35036:9"/>
Some one may, perhaps, object, That ſuch Proſelytes were all raſh and inconſtant Barbarians, who ſuddently took up a new Faith, and as eaſily parted again with it, having Entred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a Religion of which they ſcarce knew more than the Name. Whatever place this Cavil might find in other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions, it hath none in theſe; not one ſmall Village that <hi>Xa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verius</hi> Converted, ever abandoned the Faith ſo miraculouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, except the only Town of <hi>Tolo,</hi> which yet ſoon reſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it, and ever ſince conſtantly retained it. Such was the ſervor of <hi>Xaverius</hi>'s Neophites, that many Slaves he had Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> piſcariâ Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. V. X. lib. 6.</note> eſpecially amongſt the <hi>Paravais,</hi> having recovered their Liberty, choſe to forfeit it again by returning to their old Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, rather than to loſe the opportunity of frequenting the Sacraments. Almoſt all the Inhabitants of the Iſland <hi>Manar,</hi> by an illuſtrious Martyrdom, conſigned to Poſterity their Zeal for Religion, equal to the moſt generous Inſtances of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church of Chriſt, near the whole Nation being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by their Neighbor Heathen Kings, whilſt not one would diſown his Baptiſm, the very Mothers producing their Children, and alledging their Baptiſm as a Title to Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. In <hi>Congoxima,</hi> a Kingdom of <hi>Japan,</hi> he left but a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Chriſtians, without the help or comfort ſuch new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts ſeemed to ſtand in need of from ſome Prieſt, yet not one fell off from his Faith, tho' preſſed to it by a moſt ſevere and bloody Perſecution raiſed againſt them by the <hi>Bonzies;</hi> their Blood and good Example of truly Chriſtian Virtues, ſwell'd up the number of Converts to Four hundred, and obliged their King by a ſolemn Embaſſy, to ask ſome Prieſt from the Vice-Roy of the <hi>Indies,</hi> who ſhould Confirm ſo miraculouſly eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed a Chriſtianity. Neither were his Converts only incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, unlearned and ſtupid People; He Baptized ſeveral Crowned Heads, their Families and Courts; He had the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to ſee Princes diveſted of their States and Perſonal Wealth, following him with Joy thus naked for Chriſt into Baniſhment, and that in <hi>Japan,</hi> a Country where Superſtition was raiſed to its greateſt height.</p>
            <p>What can be objected more againſt theſe <hi>Miracles,</hi> which if allowed, would not equally diſprove thoſe which the Apoſtles
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35036:10"/>
wrought? If we give belief to the one, how can we refuſe it to the other? If theſe be of force to make us Chriſtians, why ſhall not thoſe convince us as unavoidably, that we muſt be of that Catholic Religion which <hi>Xaverius,</hi> Legat <hi>à Latere</hi> of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Prieſt <hi>of the Society of JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> did profeſs himſelf a Member of, and Converted ſo many Kingdoms unto? If any one puts this difference betwixt <hi>Xaverius</hi>'s Miracles, and thoſe of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, that theſe were foreſeen by Prophets, whoſe Writings were preſerved in the Hands of the very Enemies of Chriſt; that moſt pregnant Proof for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, equally ſupports the Catholic Cauſe and <hi>Xave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi>'s Miracles; for not only <hi>Xaverius</hi>'s Aunt, a Religious Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, of eminent and approved Virtue in the Monaſtery of S. <hi>Clare</hi> at <hi>Gandia Magd. Jaſſe,</hi> by Letters perſuaded the Saints Father <note place="margin">In proc. Canon.</note> not to withdraw him from the Univerſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, on the account of the great Expences he put him unto there, becauſe (writ ſhe) he is a <hi>choſen Veſſel of God,</hi> deſigned to be <hi>the Apoſtle of a new World;</hi> but the very barbarous <hi>Indians</hi> of <hi>Travancor</hi> acknowledged him their promiſed Apoſtle, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ancient Prophecy carved by St. <hi>Thomas</hi> on a Pillar of Free-ſtone yet ſtanding there, which aſſured them, that White Men ſhould come from another World to teach them the way to Heaven, and to reſtore to its luſtre decayed Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity; when the Sea, then Eighty Miles diſtant, ſhould reach that Pillar, which it did few Years before <hi>Xaverius</hi> came thither; and <hi>Xaverius</hi> in particular was foretold by the Proto-Martyr of the <hi>Indies, Peter Couillan,</hi> at the moment that ſtuck with Darts he ſhed by many Wounds his Blood for the Name of Chriſt, Fifty Years before <hi>Xaverius</hi>'s Arrival into the <hi>Indies,</hi> Thirteen before his Birth. Now ſuch Prophecies are the moſt infallible Teſts of Miracles and Miſſions, becauſe they take off all whatever <note place="margin">Habemus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticum ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monem certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orem voce de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſa de coelo. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.</note> ſuſpicion of private Ends, which incredulous Men are willing to faſten on actual Miracles, as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> obſerves; which made St. <hi>Peter</hi> own ſuch Prophecies to be <hi>more certain than a Voice coming down from Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One further Objection ſome may offer at, to wit, That theſe Miracles were wrought only in proof of thoſe common and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <note place="margin">Certiorem dixit non me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorem, non veriorem, &amp;c. <hi>Aug. Ser. 115. in Nov.</hi>
               </note> Articles of Chriſtian Religion, not in debate amongſt thoſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35036:10"/>
who have the Name of Chriſtian, and therefore are no Proof of the Catholic Faith, as to thoſe Points which are not owned by Diſſenting Sectaries. I had not believed this could have been objected, had I not met with it even in the ſtudied Writings of thoſe who pretend to Senſe, and own, I believe, no ſmall ſhare of it, but employ it unſucceſsfully in a bad Cauſe, againſt the very moſt authentic Declarations from God. Could not the <hi>Jews</hi> have returned the very ſame Objection to our Bleſſed Lord and his Apoſtles Miracles, and ſaid they were brought only to prove the Sanctity of the <hi>Law</hi> which he owned that <hi>he came not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Non veni le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem ſolvere ſed adimplere.</note> 
               <hi>to break or repeal, but to fulfil.</hi> Again, If Miracles may thus be wrought in Confirmation of ſome Points only of a Doctrin, falſe otherwiſe in others and erroneous, how happens it, that <hi>no one ever,</hi> who was not a Catholic, happening to be in thoſe Countries by the occaſion of Reformed Plantations, could work a Miracle to perſuade thoſe Infidels of the truth of Chriſtian Religion. But to clear this important Point, there is not an Article of Catholic Belief, not a Part of Catholic Practice, which this Saint hath not proved by evident <hi>Miracles,</hi> to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed by, and acceptable to God. To inſtance in few.</p>
            <p>If Devotion to the <hi>bleſſed Virgin,</hi> and the <hi>Roſary</hi> in particular, be a part of Catholic Belief and Practice; this Saint Confirmed it by an evident Miracle, when at <hi>Meliapor</hi> giving his Beads to a Merchant then Sailing off, he ſaid to him, <hi>'Twill not be of ſmall uſe, be but devout to the Virgin Mary:</hi> For the Ship ſplit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on a Rock, this Merchant and ſome few others reached it; then on a Plank committed themſelves again to the mercileſs Waves, to eſcape certain Death by Famine: He ſaid his Beads, the only comfort or hope then left him being in that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, and <hi>Xaverius</hi>'s Prediction; when on a ſudden, after a ſhort Extaſie, in which he ſeemed to Converſe with S. <hi>Xaverius,</hi> he found himſelf alone on the Shore, without knowing where he loſt his Companions, who periſhed all in the Stormy Waves.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Invocation</hi> and <hi>Litanies of Saints</hi> be our Practice, he hath proved both to be acceptable to God; for a little Prayer-Book, containing only the Saints Litanies, being left by him with the Princeſs of <hi>Ekandono,</hi> applied by her to her Lord, ſuddenly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered him from the Agony and Convulſions of Death, and reſtored him to perfect Health.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:35036:11"/>
If we Honor their <hi>Relics,</hi> 'twas his <hi>Reliquary</hi> the Saint put uſually in his young Neophites Hands, when he ſent them to cure the Sick, or to caſt the Devils out of poſſeſt Perſons, both which they ſcarce ever failed to perform by applying it.</p>
            <p>Do we value <hi>Holy-Water?</hi> (on the account of the Holy Churches Bleſſing, and the Prayers ſaid over it) Arm'd with it alone he Encountred thoſe Tygers, who in numerous Troups came out of their Foreſt in the Iſland <hi>Sancian,</hi> and ever devoured thoſe <hi>Portugueſes</hi> who ventured out of their Trenches: Caſting it at them, he ſo put them to flight, that they have not ſince been ſeen in that Iſland.</p>
            <p>Do we believe God is Honor'd by our <hi>Vows,</hi> but moſt ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly by the Holy <hi>Sacrifice of the Maſs?</hi> It was by vowing a certain number of Maſſes, that this Saint in a moment conquered the ſtubborn Heart of a Great Man at <hi>Malaca,</hi> recalling him from an impious Deſpair the whole City was equally ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized and afflicted at, and diſpoſing him to a due Contrition, a firm Confidence in the Sacred Merits, and precious Blood of Chriſt, a happy Death.</p>
            <p>Are <hi>Pilgrimages</hi> to Places of particular Devotion in uſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, as approved by the pious Practice of all Ages and Chriſtian Nations? This Saint undertook one of Fifty Miles to the Sepulchre of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> and God approved his Devotion by a Revelation of his Divine Will, touching what he asked to be directed in.</p>
            <p>The Gift of <hi>Prophecy</hi> he often made uſe of, to call upon the <hi>Prayers of the Faithful for the Dead</hi> at the moment they depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Life, at a vaſt diſtance of Place, as in particular for <hi>John Galvan,</hi> and at another time for <hi>John d'Araos,</hi> two <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugueze</hi> Merchants.</p>
            <p>If we <hi>Honor</hi> the glorious Trophy of <hi>our Redeemer's Croſs,</hi> he planted it in almoſt all the Towns and High-ways of the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> and of ſeveral Kingdoms of <hi>Japan.</hi> Such Miracles were wrought in favor of thoſe who reſorted to them, that in their preſence they might adore their Crucified Lord, as raiſed a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Devotion in all thoſe pious <hi>Neophites</hi> towards that glorious Standard, the Pledge of <hi>Jeſus</hi>'s Victories over Sin and Death; So that the Chriſtians of <hi>Amboyno,</hi> Beſieged in their Caſtle by the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35036:11"/>
               <hi>Javares,</hi> a Heatheniſh and Barbarous Nation, unconcerned for themſelves, only ſought to withdraw from the Savage Fury of their Enemies, that <hi>Croſs</hi> which <hi>Xaverius</hi> had arbor'd there, well knowing that <hi>Jeſus</hi> could equally be Honored or Inſulted over in his Croſs. They covered it with Cloth of Gold, and hid it under Ground, then opened their Gates to their Enemies; who having ſought in vain the Croſs, could not prevail with any one, even of the weaker Sex or tendereſt Age, to diſcover where it lay; tho' moſt of them were maimed, many killed for that Refuſal.</p>
            <p>I conclude with an Obſervation of St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> on Miracles; which he ſays are wrought either <hi>per publicam Juſtitiam,</hi> or <hi>per</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. octog. trium Q Q.</note> 
               <hi>ſigna publicae Juſtitiae;</hi> that is, by a Virtue which God publiſhes to the World, or by the <hi>Signs, Sacraments, Practices</hi> of Piety and Virtue. That is, whenever a Miracle is wrought, 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, either that the Perſon, or that which he uſes or would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade to, is very Holy, and that God declares it ſo. Take whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you pleaſe: Do theſe Miracles wrought by <hi>Xaverius</hi> prove <hi>him</hi> a Saint, a Servant of God, who had intimate Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with his Lord, was highly favored by him? If ſo, can any one be perſuaded, that ſo holy a Man uſed not his ſincereſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors to attain the Knowledge of the true Faith and Religion, or that God, who ſo extraordinarily favored him, refuſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal unto him ſo important a Truth? Can we conceive a Man of a Sanctity ſo approved by Almighty God, to have been an Idolater, a Man of an unſound Faith? Superſtitious, Ignorant, Deluded? If you had rather conclude the Means he uſed in the working of theſe Prodigies, were holy, and that God declared them ſuch, it follows, That all Catholic Devotions and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, and thoſe Points of Belief from which they naturally flow, in which all Sectaries diſſent from us, are very holy, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by the Divine Authority of Miracles.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs, I cannot conceive what a Thinking Man can yet object to theſe Miracles wrought by <hi>Xaverius,</hi> whereby he may leſſen the Obligation laid on him to betake himſelf to the Boſom of that <hi>Catholic</hi> Church, to the Sincerity of whoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin only, to the Piety of whoſe Practices God gives ſo mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous an Approbation as all theſe Prodigies make up!</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:35036:12"/>
Can it be objected by any particular Man, that <hi>he himſelf hath ſeen no one of like Miracles?</hi> This would be as plauſible a Plea for an Atheiſt againſt the Miracles of Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. <hi>Herod</hi> himſelf, if this be received, is not guilty for mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Erat cupiens ſignum Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere.</note> our Bleſſed Lord; he never ſaw him work a Miracle, tho' he much deſired and ſought it from Chriſt himſelf. 'Tis the ſame Impiety to require a freſh Miracle for the truth of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Belief, after theſe ſo publickly wrought by <hi>Xaverius,</hi> as to exact the like in proof of Chriſt's Divinity, after thoſe which he and his Apoſtles wrought. And conſidering the Converſions in the greateſt part of the new World, effected by <hi>Xaverius</hi>'s Miracles, I cannot but ſay to ſuch an one in St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi>'s words, <note n="*" place="margin">Accepimus Majores no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtros viſibilia miracula ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quutos eſſe, per quos id actum eſt ut neceſſaria non eſſent poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.—Nec jam nobis eſſe dubium debet iis eſſe creden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum qui cum ea praedicarent quae pauci aſſequuntur, ſe tamen ſequendos populis perſuadere potuerunt. <hi>Aug. de ver. Relig. cap.</hi> 25. Quiſquis etiam num quaerit prodigium, magnum eſt ipſe prodigium, qui mundo credente non credit. <hi>De Civit. Dei, l. 22. c. 8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>We are taught that our Anceſtors followed viſible Miracles, after which none others are neceſſary to guide us: We cannot doubt but that we ought to believe thoſe</hi> Apoſtles, <hi>who Preaching ſuch things as few can conceive or reach, yet perſuaded whole Nations to follow them:</hi> For, what Doctrin it was <hi>Xaverius</hi> confirmed by his Miracles, is a known thing, and out of debate. <hi>Whoever after ſuch, requires yet a Miracle, is to me himſelf a great Prodigy, who refuſes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, what a World doth not doubt of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know ſome will object, That ſhould an Angel come from Heaven to teach them otherwiſe than the Goſpel doth, we ought even not to return him any other Anſwer than <hi>Anathema;</hi> That Miracles are then only to be conſidered and valued, when the Doctrin in favor whereof they are wrought, is known to be true and ſound. This had been an excellent Plea for the Scribes and Phariſees againſt Chriſt. The <hi>Jews</hi> had a poſitive Command to believe no Worker of <hi>Miracles, (Deut. 13.)</hi> that ſhould teach them a Doctrin contrary to what they had received from <hi>Moſes;</hi> they were bid, in Doubts of that nature, to have their recourſe to the High-Prieſt, and they forfeited their Life who refuſed to obey him. The Scribes, Phariſees, Prieſts judging of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of Chriſt by his Doctrin, condemned both, as when he Cured upon the Sabbath-day, and reproached him as a Magician,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35036:12"/>
for caſting out Devils in the Power of Beelzebub. Did Chriſt alter his Method? Did he prove the reality of his Miracles by the ſoundneſs of his Doctrin? No; but charged the <hi>Jews</hi> with the Sin of Incredulity, <hi>(Joan.</hi> 15.) chiefly for not ſubmitting themſelves to him, for not embracing his Doctrin on the account of his <hi>Miracles.</hi> Doth this Method of Chriſt contradict the Law of God? Not at all; for Chriſt oppoſed neither <hi>Moſes</hi> nor his Law, but was foretold by the one, accompliſhed the other. The <hi>Jews</hi> gave a falſe Senſe and Interpretation to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the other Patriarchs and Prophets Predictions, they pretended <hi>Chriſt</hi> miſ-expounded them; this was the Debate, in which the <hi>Jews</hi> were obliged in Conſcience to own Chriſt, to take from him the true Senſe of the Prophecies, convinced by his Miracles that God ſent and Commiſſioned him to Teach. So in our Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, ſhould any Perſon own (as Antichriſt will) that he oppoſes <hi>himſelf</hi> to Chriſt, or a <hi>new</hi> Doctrin to his eſtabliſhed one; 'tis clear, that no ſeeming Miracle could in reaſon move us to follow ſuch a Perſon, the Predictions and Miracles of Chriſt would fence us againſt all the deceitful Temptations ſuch a Perſon could offer. But when the Queſtion is, What Doctrin Chriſt did teach, (to the deciſion of which Queſtion no Miracles wrought heretofore by Chriſt can be of any uſe) when evident Miracles are wrought by thoſe who are in a poſſeſſion of the Doctrin delivered by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, ſuch Miracles as Chriſt himſelf promiſed they ſhould be impowered to work, <hi>who ſhould believe</hi> as he had taught, to plead againſt theſe, that the oppoſite Doctrin is true, therefore thoſe Miracles are of no force; and that Miracles are of no uſe, but when the Doctrin they are brought to uphold is owned and followed: This An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer hath leſs (if poſſible) of common Senſe, than he who ſhould maintain, That an excellent Antidote is of no uſe, but <note place="margin">Regula Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dend. per J. K.</note> for ſuch as have not taken any Poiſon, as are out of all danger of any Infection: Leſs than that Criminal, who having heard clear, poſitive and unqueſtionable Evidences brought in againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſhould confidently ſay in his own defence, That he cannot indeed on any ſcore reject or diſprove the Witneſſes, yet that the Judges cannot but ſee that they are not to be heard or minded, becauſe he is innocent, and no Witneſſes ought to be regarded, who depoſe againſt an innocent Perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:35036:13"/>
Thus I have ſhewed how inſignificant all the Objections are, which may be offered againſt the undoubted Authority of S. <hi>Xa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verius</hi>'s Miracles: One Scruple I will yet remove, which I have known raiſed in ſome; 'tis this. If the Authority of theſe <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles</hi> be ſo weighty, how come ſo many Learned <hi>Churchmen</hi> of our Perſuaſion not to yield to it? I could be willing to paſs by that <hi>Quaere</hi> without an Anſwer, which muſt reflect ſomewhat ſeverely on many; but I muſt not forget my meek Saviour's ſharp and ſevere Replies to thoſe Scribes and Phariſees, whoſe Credit with the People, and Infidelity, put an equal ſtop to the Converſion of the <hi>Jews.</hi> How many Scribes, Phariſees, or Jewiſh Prieſts do we read of, Converted by Chriſt? Scarce a <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> a <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> and thoſe alſo <hi>Concealed Diſciples, Night-Friends:</hi> the immediate Voice of Chriſt, his Hand, and a heavy one, were neceſſary to Convert a <hi>Saul. Xaverius</hi> affords a plain Inſtance in the Caſe; amongſt the Twelve hundred thouſand which he Inſtructed and Baptized, how many <hi>Brachmans, Bonzies,</hi> and ſuch blind Guides, that <hi>Lead</hi> others into Errors, were reckoned? But one only, or two. Then ſure to teach Errors is that Sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Holy Ghoſt, which is ſo ſeldom pardoned, as to be ſaid <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 12, 32.</note> never to be. Why then, thick is that Cloud which People ever raiſe before their Eyes who impugn Truth; and Error defended once with Heat, is commonly maintained with an incorrigible Stubbornneſs: No Miracle can equal ſuch Peoples ſtubborn In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibility, and alter them. It was ſuch Scribes and Phariſees which Chriſt ſtil'd an <hi>Evil</hi> and <hi>Adulterous</hi> Generation, <hi>to whom a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 12. 39. Generatio prava &amp; adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera ſignum, petit &amp; ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num non da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur ei.</note> 
               <hi>Miracle ſhould not be given.</hi> Many, 'tis true, were wrought in their Preſence, but of which not any one was given them, that is, no ſuch interior plentiful Grace was allowed them, as would ſo far move their ſtubborn Souls, as to ſubmit to Truth made out by ſuch Prodigies. Beſides, two other main Lets ſtop ſuch People in the purſuit of Truth; which appeared in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Paſſage. <hi>Xaverius</hi> had convinced Two hundred <hi>Brachmans</hi> of the Errors of their Law, and the Sanctity of the Chriſtian, they had owned both, all of them in one Aſſembly; The Saint hoped this Effect of Gods Grace would prove a mighty inviting Example; But he no ſooner preſſed theſe Men to own the Favor God had done them, and demand Baptiſm, than he diſcovered
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35036:13"/>
his Error. Their general Anſwer was, <hi>And what will the World</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bouhours l. 2. fol. 156.</note> 
               <hi>think of us, who have ſo long plauſibly taught ſo oppoſite a Religion? And next, who will maintain our Wives and Children?</hi> Alas! theſe are ſtill the two unconquerable Difficulties of many at this day; that are like to thoſe Diſciples of the Learned <hi>Plato,</hi> who (as St <hi>Auguſtin</hi> obſerves) <hi>Probe ſciebant,</hi> knew well that their whole Religious Frame was the Work of Man, occaſioned by, and followed on Human Deſigns: <hi>But a long and public Cuſtom had nurs'd them in it; it was eſtabliſh'd by Law, and could not eaſily be</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ex Conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine tamen publicâ quae quoniam Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus erat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmata con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velli non pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat &amp; ne po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulos offende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, <hi>&amp;c. Aug. de Civit. Dei, l. 8. c. 8. &amp; 12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>taken to pieces;</hi> in fine, <hi>not to offend the Crowd,</hi> they ſtill ſacrific'd to thoſe Idols which had no being but by the meer invention of men, by a <hi>Lay-Scripture</hi> of <hi>National Laws.</hi> And can ſuch mens Examples be of any force with conſcientious men, or prove a lett to their Converſion? But ſo much the more are to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>the Riches of the Goodneſs of God,</hi> and the force of his conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Graces, whilſt we ſee daily amongſt us thoſe in no ſmall number, who diſcerning at laſt the true Religion thro' the miſt of thoſe falſe Aſperſions and disfiguring Miſrepreſentations un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which it had ever been conceal'd from them, remove all thoſe ſtrong Prejudices inſtill'd with their firſt Education, deeper ſunk in by a ſtudious Application, ſlight the bitter Invectives and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer Raileries of thoſe whoſe Errors they relinquiſh, abandon plentiful Livings, overlook all their ancient Intereſt, the Eſteem of their Friends, the Kindneſs of their Relations, the Favours of their greateſt Supports, follow with Fidelity thro' <hi>Infamy and good Fame</hi> God's gracious Call, rejoycing with the two Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <hi>that they are judged worthy to ſuffer ſuch diſgraces for his Holy Name. ONE</hi> ſuch Example ought to counterpoiſe <hi>a thouſand,</hi> whom Human Intereſt, a darling Credit, the Spirit of Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Pride, have wedded unchangeably to their Error.</p>
            <p>Whoever, having well weigh'd the Authority of theſe Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of St. <hi>Xaverius</hi> as here diſcuſs'd, will yet refuſe to receive the Word of God from this his Apoſtle, whoſe Miſſion is by them ſo unqueſtionably proved; and will ſtill reject the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Faith which he offers, becauſe he pretends obſcurity and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty in ſome of her Myſteries: With whom can I rank ſuch, but with thoſe Jews who ſeigned to ſeek with Zeal and Concern the true Faith, ſaying to Chriſt, <hi>How long will you afflict our Soul
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:35036:14"/>
with ſuſpence by theſe obſcure uncertainties? If you are the Chriſt,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Quouſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam noſtram tollis? ſi tu es Chriſtus dic nobis palam—Loquor vobis &amp; non credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis—Opera quae ego facio in nomine Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris mei, haec teſtimonia perhibent de me, <hi>Joan.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>ſay ſo plainly to us.</hi> What anſwered our bleſſed Lord to theſe Hypocrits? <hi>I ſpeak</hi> clearly and diſtinctly enough, <hi>yet you believe not.</hi> But where, O Lord, where do you in plain and expreſs words tell them you are their expected Meſſias, and the Son of God? <hi>The Miracles I work in the Name of my Father</hi> (by my Servants) <hi>are a ſufficient witneſs to me,</hi> (to the Truth which I teach by them.) 'Tis in vain to ſeek for a clearer; we have none for the general Articles of Chriſtianity. I conclude then, that all who act reaſonably in the choice of their Religion, and own thoſe grounds to be the ſureſt which our bleſſed Lord propoſed as ſuch, and will not bottom their Salvation on any other, muſt declare themſelves neceſſarily <hi>Catholics, or no Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauperes Evangelizantur;</hi> the Poor have the Goſpel preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them. St. <hi>Hierom</hi> obſerves, That Poverty in <hi>Effect,</hi> and in <hi>Spirit,</hi> is the two-fold Character of a true Apoſtle, and the moſt unqueſtionable proof of Divine Wiſdom and Power in him, who thus qualifies thoſe he ſingles out to preach his Doctrin, and bleſſes their endeavors with a ſucceſs which could not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly attend their condition, ſo ſeemingly deſpicable, if a Divine Power ſupply'd not their want of all thoſe Materials which Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Wiſdom would judge abſolutely neceſſary for ſo great a Work. It follows, that the moſt ſurprizing of thoſe Miracles which accompanied the Apoſtles Preaching, was the Converſion of ſo great a part of the World from Errors and Vices: From <hi>Errors,</hi> ſuck'd in with the firſt Milk, eſtabliſh'd by Laws, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by Cuſtom, ſtrengthen'd by Superſtition, proportion'd to the ſhort ſight of Human Senſe and Miſapprehenſions, fitted to the univerſal Corruption of Manners, ſympathizing with the moſt general and violent Inclinations, foſtering the moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Sins. From <hi>Vices,</hi> authoriz'd by Example, heighten'd by Evil Habits, follow'd with Paſſion, chang'd into a ſecond Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And this <hi>by Men</hi> who were to teach a Doctrin that ſoars above the reach of Reaſon, that contradicts our Senſes, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a contempt of what vitious Nature moſt covets, a free choice of what ſhe moſt dreads, or repines at; and offers on all hands a ſevere Check to that looſe Liberty all men are naturally
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35036:14"/>
ſo fond of: <hi>By Men</hi> who promis'd not in this Life any of thoſe ſo-valu'd Advantages of Fortune, but rather threatned with Croſſes, Afflictions, Loſſes, Miſeries, Separation from Kindred, Relations, Friends; Contempt, Perſecution, Baniſhments, Chains, and thoſe other ſevere Trials which the Goſpel propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as a neceſſary Teſt of the ſincerity of thoſe who undertake to ſerve God: <hi>By Men,</hi> in fine, not countenanc'd by Great Ones to whoſe Ends they ſerved not, not ſupported by the Intereſt of Friends, not conſiderable by their private Fortunes, not upheld by any ſiding Faction; but Poor, Abject, unknown to all, Single, Proclaimers of harſh Truths, and appearing at firſt under the odious Character of Unknown Strangers, ſuperciliouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning the ancient Laws, Cuſtoms, Devotion, Faith, Religion of the Land. This, O this is the great Miracle, not expoſed to the leaſt Jealouſie of Forgery, to any ſuſpicion of Deceit. All theſe Circumſtances attended <hi>Xaverius</hi>'s Miſſion: He was ſent to convert a newly-diſcover'd World; the which ſavage Cruelty, blind Superſtition, and all the odious Vices which Human Souls and Bodies are capable of, held enſlav'd. With reaſon did <hi>Paul the Third,</hi> ſending St. <hi>Xaverius</hi> to the <hi>Indies,</hi> mind him that God (whenever he employs any one in a Work that ſurpaſſes Human Forces) ſupplies him with a ſtrength capable to effect whatever is impoſſible to Nature; with reaſon he warned him that he was ſent to tread on the footſteps of the firſt Apoſtle of the <hi>Indies,</hi> St. <hi>Thomas.</hi> What Preparatives, think you, are made for ſo vaſt a Conqueſt? He hath one Evenings warning al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd him to put himſelf in readineſs, and his whole Equipage is his <hi>Breviary.</hi> Truly, O Lord, theſe ſtrange Methods of yours <note place="margin">Abſcondiſti haec à ſapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus &amp; pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentibus, &amp; revelaſti ea parvulis, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. Contemptibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia primo ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git Deus ut confunderet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os qui apud homines mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni habentur, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>are hidden from the wiſe and prudent, and revealed to little ones;</hi> thus ſtill <hi>you chooſe thoſe firſt who are contemptible, to confound thoſe whom the world eſteems great.</hi> This Man, whoſe Employ is to deſtroy Idolatry in one half of the World, to root out Vices, to alter the Laws and Cuſtoms of Nations, to oppoſe himſelf to all the Corruptions of Nature and bad Habits, to change the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief and Practices of Courts and People; obſerve him well in his firſt or laſt Miſſions, and promiſe, if you can, any ſucceſs to his Undertakings. After that for ſome time he beſtow'd his Labors on the Reformation of the Chriſtians at <hi>Goa,</hi> his firſt Miſſion is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35036:15"/>
to <hi>Comorino,</hi> 600 miles diſtant; thence he paſſes to the great Kingdom of <hi>Travancor; Piſcaria</hi> is his next ſtation; whence he brings the Light of the Goſpel to the <hi>Molucan</hi> Iſlands, and thence to thoſe of <hi>Moro.</hi> Some of theſe Nations were ſo barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, that they either furiouſly ſhot with Arrows, or treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly poyſon'd, ſuch Strangers as unhappily entred their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; and fed on the Bodies of their neareſt Relations: Others, parch'd by a ſcalding Sun, ſo barren as ſcarce to yield a ſmall part of the Neceſſaries for Life: All, wholly Idolatrous, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the ſole Name of Chriſtianity, abandoned to the fouleſt Vices, barbarouſly Savage, or moſt ſtupidly Dull. Theſe <hi>Xaverius</hi> attempts to conquer; alone, without the help often of an Interpreter, or any knowledge of their Language; able on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (without a Miracle) to yield ſome mute Services to their Sick; without any Proviſion to relieve him in moſt preſſing wants; without any Human Help or Comfort; wandring thro' Deſarts; croſſing Valleys ſwell'd with floods; breaking his way thro' thick Woods, without any other Guide beſides God's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; in Hunger and Thirſt, in Sweat and Labors, in Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from ſavage Beaſts and fiercer Men. If he projects the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of <hi>Japan,</hi> what Difficulties doth not offer a Voyage of many thouſand miles, by Seas beſet with Pirates, expos'd to mercileſs Whirlwinds, full of unknown Quickſands and Rocks; no Chriſtian Power even known or heard of there, to ſupport him, or protect thoſe whom he ſhall convert. When Landed, if he goes towards the Royal City <hi>Meaco,</hi> I invite you to view this Great Champion, fitted for his Mighty Atchievements: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a poor deſpicable Man, bare-headed and bare-foot, in ragged Cloaths, and that in a Country where Poverty is held ſuch a Diſgrace, and ſo heavy a Curſe of Heaven, that they believe the Poor out of a poſſibility of being Happy even in the next Life; with one Companion and an Interpreter, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf knowing but few Words of their Language; carrying on his Back a Pack of Church-ſtuff; and for his whole Proviſion a little Rice dry'd by the fire. Thus he continues two months Journey thro' Mountains of Snow, ſuch that even in Towns no Houſe hath there any Communication with another, but by cover'd Galleries; endeavouring in every little Town to preach
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35036:15"/>
the Goſpel, beaten and kick'd out of each, dragg'd by the feet out of two, to be ſtoned to Death, if a ſudden miraculous Storm had not reſcued him, putting his Enemies to flight. Behold, being loſt in a Wood, he accepts to carry the Portmanteau of a Japonian Gentleman, only to have him for Guide, and follows him well mounted a whole day, ſweating under his double Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, till in the Evening he is found by his Companion and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter fainting under it, half dead, his Feet and Legs wounded all over with Brambles and Thorns, and covered with gore Blood. Is not this a ſad Original of a poor contemptible Wretch? Can any thing be poſſibly perform'd by ſo ſlighted a Creature, in ſuch hard Circumſtances? Humanly ſpeaking, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Yet this Man converts a conſiderable Part of different Kingdoms, ſubdues Kings and whole Courts, hath whole Towns following him into the open Fields to hear him Preach from a Tree; is offered <hi>Divine Honors</hi> by the chiefeſt <hi>Bonzies</hi> of thoſe Kingdoms; even, if he will accept them, Churches, Altars, and Sacrifices; this man converts the laſting Errors of many Ages, breaks inveterate Cuſtoms, deſtroys (there, and in other Kingdoms) 40000 Idols worſhiped in that degree of violent Superſtition, that thoſe blind Infidels offered to many Human Blood, and ſacrificed their very Children; ſubdues Hearts, Barbarous, Inhuman, Lewdly looſe, and prodigiouſly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, to Meekneſs, Humility, Chaſtity, Devotion; ſo that <hi>Iſay</hi>'s Prophetical Promiſes made to the Catholic Church, were then perfectly accompliſhed: <hi>The Children of Aliens ſhall build up thy Walls, and their Kings ſhall ſerve thee: Thou ſhalt ſuck the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aedificabunt ſilii peregri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum muros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuos, &amp; Reges eorum mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrabunt tibi, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 60. Suges lac gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milla Regum lactaberis, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.</note> 
               <hi>Milk of Nations, and the Breaſts of Kings ſhall nurſe thee.</hi> And after ſuch an Apoſtolical Converſion of Nations to Chriſtianity, can any one wiſh for a more unqueſtionable, a more convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Proof of the True Faith, and Admirable Vertues of <hi>Xa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verius?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But obſerve now with me, How highly he values that ſtrange diſproportion of his Condition and his Employ! what a Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Abjection, what Sufferings he courts! the moſt certain Mark of a true Apoſtle. 'Tis the firſt evident Proof which St. <hi>Paul</hi> gave of his Miſſion, <hi>a complete Patience;</hi> that is, which <hi>loves</hi> the Burden that it <hi>bears.</hi> One night <hi>Xaverius</hi> ſleeping in <note place="margin">In omni pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entià, 2 <hi>cor.</hi> 12.</note>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:35036:16"/>
the ſame Chamber with Father <hi>Simon Rodriguez</hi> (who firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mplius, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</note> in <hi>Portugal</hi> the Name of <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> and bequeath'd it to his whole Order) was obſerv'd by him with a moſt preſſing eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to cry out often, <hi>More! Oh more, Lord!</hi> Tho' often im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portun'd, he would never open to Father <hi>Rodriguez</hi> the occaſion and meaning of thoſe words; till taking his laſt leave of him at his Embarquing for the <hi>Indies,</hi> he owned that God had then of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered him a large view of vaſt Seas ſwell'd with Billows, torn with Tempeſts, covered with Shipwrecks; of deſerted Iſlands, of barbarous Wilderneſſes, and every where Want, Poverty, Hunger, Thirſt, Weariſomneſs, Dangers, Perſecutions, Sweat, and Toil; thus diſcovering to him what he was to ſuffer for his holy Name. Behold a double Picture of <hi>Xaverius;</hi> a double Proſpect, the one of his Life, the other of his Mind; that full of Sufferings, Wants, Miſeries; this of a high value for ſo holy tho' ſo heavy a Croſs. What was the whole Treaſure of this <hi>Legat à Latere</hi> of the Pope, ſent to a whole New World? An old patch'd Caſſock, a Mat to lie on, a little Box of Writings and Catechiſms, a Crucifix, a Breviary, a Hair-ſhirt, Iron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Chains, and Diſciplines. Behold the whole Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory!</p>
            <p>From the beginning he courted Want and Miſery. His firſt perpetual Vow made at <hi>Venice,</hi> in the hands of His <hi>Holineſs's Nuncio Veralli,</hi> was of <hi>Poverty.</hi> Next, to prepare himſelf to his firſt <hi>Maſs,</hi> he withdrew to <hi>Monſelire</hi> near <hi>Padua,</hi> for forty days, where he took up in a forlorn Hovel, deſerving well the Name he gave it of his <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> where expoſed to all the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Air, he lay on the cold ground, begging the little Bread he eat. His following ſtation was at <hi>Bolonia,</hi> where tho' he labour'd inceſſantly the whole Day, and pray'd the beſt part of the Night, yet he refuſed the preſſing Charity of thoſe who offer'd him their Table, and accepted only what Bread he begg'd from door to door. The Count of <hi>Caſtagnera</hi> enquiring of him in the King's Name what he likely would want in his long Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to the <hi>Indies,</hi> urging him to uſe freely his Maſter's Royal Bounty, had this anſwer from him, <hi>My Lord, he wants nothing who ſtands in need of nothing; I owe much to His Majeſty's gracious care for me, but much more to my God's Providence; you will not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35036:16"/>
me from relying on it, and on it only, till it abandons me.</hi> On Ship-board he refus'd the Vice-Roy's Table, and liv'd of what he begg'd in the Sip, where he cook'd the poor Souldiers and Paſſengers Meat, waſh'd their Linen, ſerv'd day and night the Sick, laying them in the Chamber and on the Bed aſſigned for him, ſleeping himſelf ever on the Cables. When from <hi>Goa</hi> he begun his firſt Miſſion of 600 miles, all the Vice-Roy could ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige him to accept of towards it, was one pair of Shoes to keep off the exceſſive heats of burning Sands.</p>
            <p>I know ſome, leſs acquainted with the ſecrets of God, will ask, what need there was of ambitioning ſo naked a Poverty? Why there ſhould be ſo much Virtue, where there appears ſo little Diſcretion? Why Human helps ſhould be caſt away, as if it were not enough to obey that Scripture, <hi>If you abound with</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Divitiae ſi aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluant, nolite cor apponere, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 61. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Riches, faſten not your heart to them?</hi> Such men have forgot our Bleſſed Lord's Inſtructions given to his Apoſtles, when he firſt ſent them to preach. They are, I fear, as little diſpoſed to ſeek true Perfection, as the young man in <hi>Matthew</hi> 19. 1. who counſell'd by Chriſt to <hi>ſell all, give it to the poor, and follow him;</hi> not able now to pretend Ignorance, ſteptback, and dejected at the very thought of abandoning all, withdrew from Chriſt. I know that is a <hi>harſh word</hi> to thoſe that live at eaſe, and would willingly compound with God for <hi>ſome part,</hi> when he adviſes the giving up of the <hi>whole.</hi> And ſince it was a principal part of the Godly <hi>Reformation</hi> by ſuppreſſing all Religious Houſes, to aboliſh the very Memory of Voluntary Poverty, no wonder if the Teachers in a Congregation grounded on Principles ſo op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the Counſels of Chriſt, cannot produce <hi>One</hi> in their nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Multitude who would ever ſerve God <hi>gratis,</hi> and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly follow this, or any other <hi>Evangelical Counſel.</hi> No; God would not permit that ſo holy an Imitation of <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſhould make a part of their <hi>Sheeps-cloathing.</hi> But ſure thoſe who diſcover not in this two-fold Poverty a Divine Vertue, have forgot the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition thoſe Men of God liv'd in even under the Old Law, <hi>of which the World was not worthy;</hi> they forget in the New the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty <note place="margin">Circuierunt in melotis in pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus caprinis, egentes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtiati, <hi>&amp;c. Heb.</hi> 11. 37.</note> of Jeſus from <hi>Bethlehem</hi> to <hi>Calvary;</hi> from the poor Hovel he was laid in the Manger of: to the borrowed Sepulcher he was laid in; they forget that the Happy in the firſt Rank amongſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35036:17"/>
               <hi>Jeſus</hi>'s Diſciples are the <hi>Poor of Spirit,</hi> who by this Vertue have a juſt Claim to Heaven; they forget the Apoſtles <hi>firſt,</hi> left not only Unlawful Gains, and the <hi>Publican</hi>'s Counter, but alſo both their <hi>Boat</hi> and their <hi>Net,</hi> that is, the enjoyment of preſent Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, and the hopes or deſires of future Purchaſes; and then were imitiated by all the faithful Believers, who laid at the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles feet without any reſerve, (the ſin of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira)</hi> after ſo holy a Profeſſion, the value of all they had. Theſe, theſe our Apoſtle did imitate, not without an infinity of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Motives. He believed Chriſt teaching him that Riches and Wealth are <hi>Thorns,</hi> and it would have been impoſſible to have over-run all the Eaſt as he did, in a way ſtrew'd with Thorns. His Life was ſhort, only ten years being allotted him to preach the Goſpel to above twenty Kingdoms or Nations; he was then following the Apoſtle's Advice, <hi>to redeem time becauſe the days are</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. Etiam cum detrimento corporalium commodorum ad quaerenda &amp; capeſcenda bonaaeterna, ſpatia tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris comparare, <hi>Hom. 1, &amp; 10. Ex.</hi> 50, Ipſi mundo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mnes divitiae, omnes digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, &amp; uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſarum cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piditatum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriae refun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantur, &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto beatoque commercio e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana Libertas fiant<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Filii Dei de pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertate divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, <hi>&amp;c. Ep. ad Demet.</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctius terrena conſtringunt adepta quam concupita,—Illa velut ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tranea repudiantur; iſta velut membra poſſidentur, <hi>Ep. 34. ad Pauli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>evil;</hi> that is, ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> to withdraw the leaſt part of it from the anxious cares of acquiring, increaſing, preſerving Earthly Goods, that all may be beſtowed on the ſeeking and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Eternal Bliſs. He was to break the Chains of others; and conſequently, firſt to ſecure to himſelf a full Liberty; fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing that advice of St. <hi>Proſper, Let the Children of God return to the World its Riches and Dignities, the food of all our ſenſual de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and by a holy and bleſſed Trafique buy Chriſtian Liberty rich in their Poverty,</hi> and the contempt of tranſitory things; <hi>which,</hi> as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> obſerves, <hi>'tis eaſier to ſlight when diſpoſſeſs'd of them, than not to love whil'ſt we enjoy them: Thoſe we eaſily reject, as not belonging to us; theſe we hugg, as our own members and parts of us.</hi> For theſe reaſons <hi>Xaverius,</hi> by the help of God's Grace, moſt Poor <hi>in Effect,</hi> Poorer <hi>in Spirit,</hi> meaſur'd ſeveral times the whole Extent of the <hi>Indies,</hi> content in his Sufferings, happy in his Wants, till in the Iſland of <hi>Sanciano</hi> he died, as he had lived, as poor, as abandoned as an Apoſtle, in an open Cottage, on a poor Mat, deſtitute of all Human Help or Comfort, having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Earth to leave but his Body, the readier to take poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of that Kingdom of Heaven to which he had ſo good a Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Evangelical</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Poverty.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:35036:17"/>
               <hi>Beatus qui non fuerit ſcandalizatus in me.</hi> Thrice happy is he to whom the Poverty, the Abjection, the Croſs of Chriſt is not a Scandal that frights from his Service, who dares ſeek in them the Gifts of God; in what an unmeaſurable proportion doth he receive them! Witneſs <hi>Xaverius,</hi> who might have wrote from almoſt each part of the <hi>Indies</hi> what he writ from the moſt miſerable Coaſt of <hi>Piſcaria,</hi> where Nature ſeemed to have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got to provide for the Neceſſities of the Inhabitants. <hi>If there be true Joy poſſeſſed on Earth, 'tis that which they experience who labor here; I hear one ſay ſometime, O Lord, moderate your Favors here below, or take me to your ſelf; 'tis too ſevere a Puniſhment thus to love, and to live thus far from you.</hi> Theſe Joys his Heart then ſwelled with, when he ſingle and alone, had all the Sick of that Coaſt to Tend, all the Afflicted to Comfort, the Ignorant to Inſtruct, the Sacraments to Adminiſter to all; ſo that he ſeldom could allow himſelf three Hours to reſt. Theſe interior Joys ever attended him at the holy Altar, and when he was at his Meditations, often forced him to rip open the Cloaths that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered his Breaſt, and by the application of cold Water to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate thoſe Divine Flames that conſumed his Breaſt, ever ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out amorouſly, <hi>Enough, O Lord, this is more than frail Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can ſupport.</hi> Even when all the Powers of his Soul were oppreſſed with Sleep, that habitual Flame raiſed ſuch pious Dreams, as forced from him devout Expreſſions of his tender Love for God; when awake, his Soul was ſo entirely poſſeſſed with that Love, that Rays of Glory frequently environed his Face, bright Glimmerings of that pure Flame within; which drew ſo violently his Soul towards Heaven, as to heave frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his Body from the Earth, eſpecially at that admirable Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Love, the Holy <hi>Maſs.</hi> No wonder he ſhould paſs the whole Night, when on Land, at the Foot of Altars in Churches, or in ſome Grove, where he could give a larger ſcope to his warm Affections. No wonder, when at Sea, he ever ſhould be abſorpt in Contemplation from Midnight to Sun-riſing; du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which time the Seamen never ſeared a Storm; That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the two Hours of fixed Meditation which he ſtole from his daily Apoſtolical Labors, even in theſe his Mind ſhould be ſo lodged where his Love ever dwelt; that his God never
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35036:18"/>
was entirely ecclipſed from his ſight. If then Virtue, according to St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi>'s Definition, <hi>be nothing elſe but well ordered Love;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Definitio bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis &amp; vera virtutis eſt ordo amoris. <hi>De Civit. l. 15. c,</hi> 22. Ille dilectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis nobis ordo ſervandus eſt, Deum principaliter diligamus, &amp; propter ipſum &amp; in ipſo ea quae diligenda ſunt quantum ipſe praecipit diligamus. <hi>l. 3. 10. V. cont. Apocal.</hi> 3. 18.</note> how great was this Saint's Virtue, that put ſo great a diſtance in his Love betwixt God and all things elſe, that they all vaniſhed frequently from his Thoughts, whilſt God only ever reigned in his Heart? If the Second Duty of Charity be to love all things elſe <hi>for Gods ſake, in view only of the Report which they have to him,</hi> and <hi>in the Meaſure he requires,</hi> as St. <hi>Proſper</hi> obſerves; how perfect was the Love of <hi>Xaverius</hi> for God, when for his ſake he embraced ſo tenderly what Nature ſo much loaths, ſo much abhors? As Toils, Want, Diſgraces, Dangers, Pains, Death; and even hated all what Senſe is charmed with, or what natural Inclinations moſt affect, whenever it failed that they oppoſed the increaſe of his Charity. This, this is the ſureſt Teſt, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Proof of a Divine and truly Apoſtolical Miſſion, that richeſt of Gods Gifts, that <hi>Flaming Gold</hi> ſo prized in the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,</hi> the Love of God.</p>
            <p>The Second unqueſtionable Mark by which, if we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve our Bleſſed Lord, his true Diſciples are to be diſcerned, is their tender Love for their Neighbor, a paſſionate Zeal for <note place="margin">In hoc cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent omnes quod diſcipuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mei iſtis ſi di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectionem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bueritis ad invicem. <hi>Joan.</hi> 13.</note> his Salvation. In this Virtue <hi>Xaverius</hi> perfectly Copied the great Apoſtle of the Gentiles. His Voyages over moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Seas, and his Journeys ever afoot by Land, in the purſuit of ſuch Sinners as wandered from God, led him ſo far in Ten Years time, that he might with a far flower Motion have gone <hi>often</hi> round the Globe of the Earth: Yet in the Tranſports of his Zeal he deſigned (as his Letters witneſs) not only to Preach the Goſpel to the vaſt Empire of <hi>China</hi> and <hi>Tartary,</hi> but after he had ſubdued thoſe to the ſweet Yoke of Chriſt, to return thence by the <hi>North</hi> into <hi>Europe,</hi> that he might retrieve thoſe Loſt, recover thoſe Separated Hereticks, and gather them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain within the Pales of that <hi>One Sheepfold</hi> of the Catholic Church, where they ſhould hear again with due Submiſſion the <hi>Voice</hi> of their <hi>own</hi> only <hi>Shepherd.</hi> Nothing could fright his Zeal, not the three Shipwrecks he had ſuffered, not the Danger he had run, like another St. <hi>Paul,</hi> for three Days and Nights expoſed on a narrow Plank to the mercy of the moſt boiſtrous Waves, and loudeſt Storms. He often dream'd before he was
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35036:18"/>
deſigned for the Converſion of the new World, that he carried an <hi>Indian</hi> on his Shoulders; he groaned under that Burden. 'Twas not One, but a Million of them he bore after in his Heart, weeping often moſt bitterly when he reflected on the almoſt inevitable danger of Eternal Miſery they unhappily were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed unto. He highly valued the Converſion of any one ſingle Soul, rightly apprehending its worth, Redeemed with the moſt precious Blood of his Saviour, and capable to love and poſſeſs God for all Eternity. Hence he ſuddenly engaged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a long Sea-Voyage, only to uſe that Opportunity of winning to a true Repentance <hi>One</hi> ſingle looſe Liver who was on Shipboard. To retrieve three Souldiers from their wicked Life, he conſined himſelf for a whole <hi>Lent</hi> to their moſt uneaſie Company Day and Night. He ſent word to the only two im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent Sinners he had left at <hi>Ternate,</hi> that whenever they ſhould let him know that they had a thought of Repenting, and altering their lewd Life, he ſhould inſtantly repair to them from the utmoſt Extremity of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> to favor their pious Diſpoſition, and direct them in ſo happy a Deſign. He ſeemed comfortleſs, when he obſerved that ſome Merchants, led by Covetouſneſs, had diſcovered Countries, to which his Zeal for the Inſtruction of the Ignorant and Converſion of Sinners, had not yet brought him. As long as he found Children to Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe, <hi>Europeans</hi> to Preach unto, <hi>Indians</hi> to Inſtruct, unmindful of himſelf, he joyned Nights unto Days in thoſe Apoſtolical Functions, without allowing his wearied Body and decayed Spirits the leaſt refreſhment of Food or Reſt: Then, and then only, he conceived himſelf, with the bleſſed Martyr <hi>Ignatius,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Nunc incipio eſſe diſcipulus Chriſti. <hi>S. Ig. Epiſt. ad Rom.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to begin to be a Diſciple of Chriſt,</hi> a Member of the <hi>Society of JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All other Virtues ever wait on their Queen, <hi>Charity.</hi> They were in <hi>Xaverius</hi> in as large a meaſure: His <hi>Humility</hi> was ſo unfeigned and great, that he never blamed the Stubbornneſs, Blindneſs, or other ill Diſpoſitions of thoſe Souls, in whoſe Converſions his Endeavors were fruſtrated, or who oppoſed the progreſs of the Goſpel, but ſincerely perſuaded that his Sins put the whole obſtruction to Gods Graces, condemned himſelf to ſevere Penances for their Expiation. Tho' the Character of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35036:19"/>
               <hi>Legat à Latere</hi> from his Holineſs, ſeemed to add ſuch a Luſtre to his Miſſion, and on ſeveral occaſions could favor his Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Attempts, yet his Humility never permitted him to publiſh it, or to uſe the Power it conferred, ſave once not long before his Death; when he conceived that nothing elſe could open him an Entrance into the Empire of <hi>China,</hi> which the Avarice and Envy of <hi>Alvares,</hi> Governor of <hi>Malaca,</hi> had ſhut up.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Obedience</hi> was ſo ready, ſo punctual, ſo nicely exact, that he conſulted his Superior and Father, St. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> on every occaſion, even at that vaſt diſtance, and never ſwerved from his preciſe Orders; acknowledging that the leaſt Letter of the Alphabet, the leaſt <hi>i,</hi> which in <hi>Latin</hi> ſignifies <hi>Go,</hi> dropt from <hi>Ignatius</hi>'s Pen, ſhould move him to abandon, without the leaſt reluctancy, his greateſt Enterpriſes for the Glory of God; tho' at the ſame inſtant the largeſt proſpect of certain Hopes, the faireſt appearance of Succeſs, ſhould Court his Stay; yet that ſmall Letter ſhould lead him with Joy to any part even of the unhabitable World.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Chaſtity</hi> was ſo <hi>Entire,</hi> that his Confeſſors judged him to have preſerved that <hi>tender Virginity</hi> unſullied, without the leaſt Blemiſh. So well <hi>guarded,</hi> that when the Enemy not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to aſſail him awake, attempted by immodeſt Dreams to diſturb the innocent Repoſe of his Soul, the violent motion of his Body in rejecting from him thoſe <hi>Phantômes</hi> of tempting Objects, and the more eager reluctancy of his Soul, made him bleed.</p>
            <p>To omit the Particulars of his other Vertues, I ſhall conclude with the Maxim and Practice which gave them their firſt birth, favored their growth, and preſerved them in their full luſtre. This great Principle of a Chriſtian Life he had learnt from St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> at his firſt Converſion, it had from that moment been deeply engrave in his Memory, and the ſenſe of it in his Heart: <note n="a" place="margin">Tantum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum tibi ipſi vim intuleris.</note> 
               <hi>Your Self-denials, your Mortifications, the violence you uſe in curbing your own Inclinations, are the meaſure of your advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Gods Service.</hi> He knew that <hi>Sacrifices</hi> have ever been the chiefeſt part of Divine Worſhip, and that no Victims are ſo acceptable as a mortified, <note n="b" place="margin">Cor contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum &amp; humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liatum Deus non deſpicies. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.</note> a <hi>contrite and humble Heart.</hi> He had learnt from our Bleſſed Lord, how the Kingdom of God,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35036:19"/>
that eſpecially of his particular Graces and Favors poſſeſſing and guiding our Hearts, ſaid therefore by Chriſt to be <note n="c" place="margin">Regnum Dei intra nos eſt.</note> within us, <note n="d" place="margin">Regnum Dei vim pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; violenti rapiunt illud.</note> 
               <hi>ſuffers violence,</hi> and thoſe only attain to it, who uſe ſuch force; that <hi>who loves his Soul will loſe it,</hi> and <hi>who hates his Soul</hi> ſeemingly, by a ſevere and hard uſage, <hi>will preſerve it to Eternal Life;</hi> and eſteemed <hi>thoſe happy,</hi> with S. Auguſtin, <note n="e" place="margin">Si male a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantris tunc odiſti, ſi bene oderis, tunc amaſti; feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces qui cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diunt odiendo perdant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manda. <hi>Aug. Tract. 51. in Joan.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>who ſupport by that holy hatred, what by an indulging love they had deſtroyed;</hi> he knew that ſuch Mortifications ſerve to ſtop thoſe violent Inclinations which bear away our Souls from all attention to our Spiritual and Eternal Concerns, riveting them, as it were, in Temporal and Senſual ones; that ſuch Affections being by thoſe exterior checks driven back into our Hearts, increaſe mightily the ſtrength of a Soul moving with united Forces towards God. Therefore in imitation of Gods holy Servants, with a S. <hi>Paul <note n="f" place="margin">Perimat &amp; amittar uſum ejus ſcilicet perverſum quo inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus ut aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na non quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. <hi>De Doct. Chr. l. 3. c. 16.</hi>
                  </note> he chaſtized his Body</hi> with frequent bloody Diſciplines; with St. <hi>Benedict,</hi> he tore his Fleſh with Brambles and Thorny Rods, <note n="g" place="margin">Per cutis vulnera edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xit à corpore vulnus mentis quia volupta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem traxit in dolorem. <hi>G. G. l. Dial. c. 2.</hi>
               </note> by <hi>thoſe wounds of his Body applying a Salve to thoſe of his Mind, and driving away dangerous Pleaſures by Pains.</hi> With holy <hi>Judith</hi> and vertuous <hi>Anna,</hi> he covered himſelf with a rude Hair Shirt, and paſſed his Life in long continued Watching and Praying; with <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> he lay on the bare Ground, or Cables, or when moſt at eaſe, on a Matt. 'Twas by the ſame Principle he acted, when aplying his Mouth to the purulent Ulcers of the Sick he attended, he ſucked the filthy Matter out of them. Led away by the ſame, he refuſed paſſing near the Caſtle of <hi>Xavier,</hi> to ſee his loving Mother before he begun his Miſſion to a new World. And our Bleſſed Lord confirmed by a continued Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, how acceptable the Sufferings and Toils of <hi>Xaverius</hi> were; for a large Crucifix to be yet ſeen in the ſaid Caſtle, the Side, Arms and Feet, remaining yet covered with a Cruſt of Blood, did from thoſe Wounds yield abundance of it, whenever <hi>Xa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verius</hi> was in imminent Dangers, or extraordinary Toils in the <hi>Indies.</hi> That Year the Saint died it iſſued every <hi>Friday,</hi> to that which fell on the Second of <hi>December An.</hi> 1552. the Forty ſixth of his, the laſt Day of his Life on Earth, and the firſt of his, Happineſs in Heaven.</p>
            <p>But if <hi>Xaverius</hi> during the Courſe of his Miſſions, to the end of that of his Life, was ever attended by thoſe ſingular Graces
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:35036:20"/>
from Heaven, which authoriſed ſo many different Nations to give him the Title of <hi>Apoſtle;</hi> God by a <hi>ſingular</hi> Providence equally glorifying himſelf in this Saint after his Death, hath added ſuch an unqueſtionable Proof of his Miſſion, that no falſe Prophet nor Impoſtor was ever followed beyond Life by any ſhadow of it.</p>
            <p>Both Worlds know the frequent Miracles wrought, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Bleſſings obtained through his Interceſſion from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. His Body left on Earth entire, after it had been buried near three Months in quick Lime, and after at <hi>Malaca,</hi> above five more in dampiſh Earth, bleeding afreſh ſeveral Years after when hurt in the Foot, ever yielding a ſweet Perfume, is a ſufficient Inſtance, how glorious in the ſight of God his Soul is in Heaven. If <hi>Elizaeus</hi>'s his Bones were ſaid in holy Writ to <hi>Prophetize</hi> after Death, by reaſon of the Miracle wrought at their touching a dead Corps to which Life was reſtored; may I not ſay, that in <note place="margin">Boubours To. 2. V. X.</note> 
               <hi>Xaverius</hi>'s dead Body ſtill dwells an Apoſtle, ſo great Prodigies having ever waited on it. A raging Plague ceaſed ſuddenly at <hi>Malaca,</hi> when it was received there; Rocks ſplit and divided themſelves, to make way for the Ship it was conveyed in; All the Sick who ſaw it when brought to <hi>Goa,</hi> received their Health at that inſtant. And ever ſince, this Apoſtle, hath favored with miraculous Graces obtained by his Interceſſion, all Nations in the old and his new World, which have brought even <hi>Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, Jews</hi> and <hi>Infidels</hi> to his Sepulchre, to view that miraculous Body of a more miraculous Soul; which muſt force all, that ſhall ſtand to that moſt impartial Trial which our moſt Bleſſed Lord recommends to us, <hi>By their Fruits you ſhall know them,</hi> to own <note place="margin">Ex fructibus eorum cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcetis eos.</note> 
               <hi>Xaverius</hi> an <hi>Apoſtle</hi> moſt highly favored by Almighty God with moſt unqueſtionable Miracles, and equally prodigious Virtues.</p>
            <p>You are then ſtill, great Saint, you are to this Age, to our Kingdom an <hi>Apoſtle;</hi> the Miracles you wrought when on Earth, and obtained ſince, ſtill Preach the truth of that Catholic Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which you Planted in ſo many Kingdoms. We are all forced to uſe thoſe words to you, which <hi>Nicodemus</hi> ſpoke to our Bleſſed Lord when he owned him as yet but a Prophet, <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rabbi, ſcimus quia à Deo veniſti Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. <hi>Joan. 3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>We know God ſent you to Preach and Teach; for no one can do thoſe Wonders which you work, if God be not with him.</hi> Obtain,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:35036:20"/>
great Saint, obtain for this Nation a due Acknowledgment of this Truth, a pious Aſſent to it. This Kingdom hath a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Title to your Protection, ſince the Alms which your holy Father St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> gathered here, enabled him to win himſelf into your Acquaintance and Favor, and ſo to work, under God, your total Converſion to a pious Life. <hi>One Favor</hi> more then a Neighboring Kingdom that obtained the like through your Interceſſion, minds me to crave through your Merits, by the joynt Prayers of this pious Aſſembly. <hi>Marguerit of Auſtria,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter twenty years Barrenneſs, obtained from Heaven a Son, who ſits now on the Throne of <hi>France,</hi> and ſhe ever owned, that you were the Saint by whoſe Interceſſion ſhe ſought chiefly that great Bleſſing for her and her Kingdom. Theſe three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms expect a like Happineſs from our <hi>Moſt Gracious and Pious Queen;</hi> Permit not, great Saint, that your devout Clients be diſappointed in their Expectation of a <hi>Prince:</hi> May we owe to your Interceſſion ſo great a Bleſſing; a Prince, who may equal in Learning the great <hi>Alfred,</hi> in Piety St. <hi>Edward,</hi> in Proweſs the Third and Firſt of that Name, in Victories <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth, the Seventh in Wiſdom; that is, in a word, who may inherit ſoon his Royal Father's Virtues, and late his Throne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ad Majorem Dei Gloriam.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
